A Finding Aid to the Dore Ashton Papers, 1849, 1931-2010 in the Archives of American Art AAA.ashtdore
Archives of American Art
Dore Ashton papers
bulk 1952-2010
1931-2010
1849
1931-1983
AAA.ashtdore
Archives of American Art
12.8 Linear feet
The papers of Dore Ashton measure 12.8 linear feet and date from 1931-2010, with one letter in the Joseph Cornell subject file dating from 1849. The records document Dore Ashton's career as an art critic, historian and educator, with particular depth for the period of 1952 through 1990. The collection contains a small amount of biographical material, over 4.5 linear feet of correspondence, writings, subject files, printed materials, artwork, and reference photographs of artworks.
Ashton, Dore
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 7 series.
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1962-1978
Series 2: Correspondence, 1945-2010, undated
Series 3: Writings, 1952-1976, undated
Series 4: Research files, 1849, 1950-1984, 2009, undated
Series 5: Printed Materials, 1931-1981, undated
Series 6: Artwork, 1949, 1952, 1983, undated
Series 7: Photographs of Artwork, circa 1950-2010
Biographical/Historical note
Dore Ashton (1928-) is an art critic, author, and educator living in New York City. She wrote, contributed, and edited more than 30 books. Ashton was born in Newark New Jersey in 1928 and received an MFA from Harvard University in 1950. Her many books and articles focus on late 19th and 20th century art and artists. Ashton was associate editor at Art Digest from 1952-1954, and critic for Arts and Architecture at the New York Times, 1955-1960. Starting in 1962 she held several lecturing posts at various institutions including the School of Visual Arts, Cooper Union, and the New School for Social Research. She was awarded a Guggenheim fellowship in 1964 and a National Endowment for the Humanities grant in 1980. Among Ashton's books are Abstract Art Before Columbus, 1956; Poets and the Past, 1959; A Joseph Cornell Album, 1974; Yes, But…A Critical Study of Philip Guston, 1976, About Rothko, 1983; The New York School: a Cultural Reckoning, 1973; Noguchi East and West, 1992; and David Rankin: The New York Years, 2013. Dore Ashton was the first critic to develop a comprehensive and eye-witness account of the history of the Abstract Expressions.
Ashton married artist Adja Yunkers (1900-1983) in 1953, and they had two daughters Alexandra (known as Sasha) and Marina. In 1985 she married writer Matti Megged (1923-2003).
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Dore Ashton papers were donated to the Archives of American Art by Dore Ashton May 27, 1982, May 8, 1997, and June 2, 2011.
Related Archival Materials note
Among the holdings of the Archives is an oral history interview with Dore Ashton conducted November 21, 2010 by George W. Sampson, for the Archives of American Art's Elizabeth Murray Oral History of Women in the Visual Arts Project.
Dore Ashton papers are also located at Emory University Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of Dore Ashton measure 12.8 linear feet and date from 1931-2010, with one letter in the Joseph Cornell subject file dating from 1849. The records document Dore Ashton's career as an art critic, historian and educator, with particular depth for the period of 1952 through 1990. The collection contains a small amount of biographical material, over 4.5 linear feet of correspondence, writings, subject files, printed materials, artwork, and reference photographs of artworks. The bulk of the collection consists of correspondence with many artists, writers and others, including Pat Adams, James Adley, Rudolf Arnheim, Jake Berthot, Dennis Congdon, George Herbert, Remo Guidieri, Barbara Howes, Fred Licht, Joan Punyet Miro, Carl Fredrik Reutersward, and Hedda Sterne, among others. Smaller amounts of letters are from Joseph Albers, Edward Albee, Richard Avedon, Richard Diebenkorn, David Driskell, Alberto Gicometti, Philip Guston, Lillian Hellman, Alger Hiss, Bernard Malamud, Joan Miro, Robert Motherwell, Lewis Mumford, Claes Oldenburg, Oliver Sachs, and Vassilis Vassilikos.
Writings consist of transcripts of miscellaneous articles or those written for various publications. Research files include reference or research materials for books, exhibitions, individuals and various topics. Individuals and topics include Jacopo Luis Borges, Allan Kaprow, Richard Lindner, Seong Moy, Jean Tinguely, Mark Tobey, Jack Tworkov, Adja Yunkers; and Dadaism, poetry and symbolism.
Adams, Pat, 1928-; Adley, James, 1931-; Albee, Edward, 1928-; Albers, Josef; Arnheim, Rudolf; Avedon, Richard; Berthot, Jake, 1939-; Cornell, Joseph; Diebenkorn, Richard, 1922-; Driskell, David C.; Giacometti, Alberto, 1901-1966; Guidieri, Remo; Guston, Philip, 1913-1980; Hellman, Lillian, 1906-; Hiss, Alger; Howes, Barbara; Kaprow, Allan; Licht, Fred, 1928-; Lindner, Richard, 1901-; Malamud, Bernard; Miró, Joan, 1893-; Motherwell, Robert; Moy, Seong; Mumford, Lewis, 1895-1990; Oldenburg, Claes, 1929-; Reuterswärd, Carl Fredrik, 1934-; Sterne, Hedda, 1910-; Tinguely, Jean, 1925-; Tobey, Mark; Tworkov, Jack; Vasilikos, Vasilēs, 1934-; Yunkers, Adja, 1900-1983; Art criticism; Art critics; Art, Modern--20th century; Artists--United States; Dadaism; Historians; Photographs; Transcripts; Women art critics
- Biographical Material, 1962-1978, undated; 1; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Arrangement note
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material
  Scope and Contents note
  Included in series 1 are Mather Award citation materials, typed introduction of Ashton by Frances Osborn Robb at TCU Honors Week Convocation 1978, scattered financial documents, miscellaneous notes and a folder of family documents and photographs. Additional family correspondence can be found in Series 2.2 alphabetical.
  - Award Materials and Introduction, 1962, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Family Documents and Photographs, 1973-1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Financial Records - Miscellaneous Receipts, 1958-1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, 1969-1990, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1952-2010, undated; 2; 4.6 Linear feet Boxes 1-5, ov 15-16
  The series is arranged in two subseries.
  2.1: Chronological
  2.2: Alphabetical
  Contains mixed business and personal correspondence from artists, family, friends, admirers, writers, publishers, museums, and galleries; many with enclosures including small artworks, exhibition announcements, poetry, and photographs and writings by others. There is a small amount of correspondence from Ashton to others. The largest amounts of correspondence are with Pat Adams, James Adley, Rudolf Arnheim, Jake Berthot, Dennis Congdon, George Herbert, Remo Guidieri, Barbara Howes, Fred Licht, Joan Punyet Miro, Carl Fredrik Reutersward, and Hedda Sterne, among others. A small amount of correspondence (one to six letters) is from Joseph Albers, Edward Albee, Richard Avedon, Richard Diebenkorn, David Driskell, Alberto Gicometti, Philip Guston, Lillian Hellman, Alger Hiss, Bernard Malamud, Joan Miro, Robert Motherwell, Lewis Mumford, Claes Oldenburg, Oliver Sachs, and Vassilis Vassilikos. Types of correspondence include holiday cards and postcards, as well as letters. Some letters and envelopes are illustrated. Correspondence is in English, Spanish, French, Italian, German and Norwegian. Additional correspondence may be found in Series 1 biographical materials and Series 4 subject files.
  - Chronological, 1952-1983; 2.1
    Arranged chronologically
    - 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1955 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1956 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - January-November 1957 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - December 1957 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1958 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - January-May 1959 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - June-December 1959 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - January-May 1960 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - June-December 1960 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - January-March 1961 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - April-December 1961 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - 1962 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - January-April 1963 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - May-December 1963 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - 1964 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - January-September 1965 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - October-December 1965 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - January-March 1966 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - April-October 1966 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - November-December 1966 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - January-June 1967 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - July-September 1967 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - October-December 1967 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - January-February 1968 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - March-December 1968 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - January-March 1969 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - April-October 1969 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - November-December 1969 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - January-March 1970 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - April-July 1970 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - August-December 1970 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - 1971 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - January-October 1972 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - November-December 1972 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - January-August 1973 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - September-December 1973 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - 1974 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - January-May 1975 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - June-December 1975 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - January-March 1976 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - April-June 1976 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - July-December 1976 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - January-February 1977 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - March-April 1977 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - May-December 1977 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - 1978 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - January-June 1979 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - July-December 1979 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - January-August 1980 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - September-December 1980 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - January-February 1981 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - March-May 1981 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - June-December 1981 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Alphabetical, 1952-2010, undated; 2.2
    Arranged alphabetically by surname initial or full surname of person sent to
    - A, 1953-2009 (Box 1, Folder 60-61)
      Correspondents include Edward Albee, Josef Albers, Pierre Alechinsky and Richard Avedon.
    - Adami, Valerio, 1984-2010 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Adams, Pat, 1956-2008 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Adley, James, 1993-2007 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Arnheim, Rudolf, 1972-2002 (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
    - Ashton, Dore to William Dworkin, 1945-1947, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Ashton, Sylvia Smith Shapiro, 1955-1968 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - B, 1957-2009 (Box 2, Folder 6-9)
      Correspondents include Alfred Barr, Roland Barthes, Elizabeth Bishop and James Brooks.
    - Berthot, Jake, 1976-2010 (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
    - C, 1955-2009 (Box 2, Folder 12-14)
      Correspondents include Anthony Caro, Michael Corris.
    - Congdon, Dennis, 1988-2010 (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
    - D, 1970-2006 (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
      Correspondents include Stephen De Satebler, Richard Diebenkorn, Jim Dine, Piero Dorazio and David Driskell.
    - Davenport, Guy, 1973-1999 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - E, 1965-2009 (Box 2, Folder 20-21)
    - Escobedo, Helen, 1985-2005 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - F, 1953-2008 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
      Correspondents include Morton Feldman, S. Lane Faison and Carolos Fuentes.
    - Forge, Andrew, 1973-2002 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - de Francia, Peter, 1973-2008 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - G, 1952-2010 (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
      Correspondents include Adolph Gottlieb, Robert Graves and Serge Guilbaut.
    - George, Herbert, 1976-2008 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Giacometti, Alberto, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Goto, Joe, 1966-1992, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Greene, Stephen, 1964-1995 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Guidieri, Remo, 1986-2009 (Box 3, Folder 11-12)
    - Gustafson, Christian, 1988-2008 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Guston, Philip, 1978, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - H, 1969-2010 (Box 3, Folder 15-18)
      Correspondents include David Hare, Barbara Hepworth, Lillian Hellman, Alger Hiss, and Sam Hunter.
    - Hammacher, Abraham Marie [Bram], 1962-2001 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Hartnett, Susan, 2001-2010 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Howes, Barbara, 1960-1990 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - I, 1976-2010 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - J, 1989-2007 (Box 3, Folder 23-24)
      Correspondents include Alfredo Jaar, Ray Johnson.
    - Jeannet, Frederic-Yves, 1998-2008 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - K, 1965-2010 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
      Correspondents include Ellsworth Kelly, Stanley Kunitz.
    - L, 1973-2010 (Box 4, Folder 4-7)
      Correspondents include Jack Lenore Larsen and Richard Lindner.
    - Licht, Fred, 1973-2003, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Lynton, Norbert, 1983-2007 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - M, 1964-2010 (Box 4, Folder 10-12)
      Correspondents include Bernard Malamud, W.S. Merwin, and Robert Motherwell.
    - Megged, Matti, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Miro, Joan, Delores and Joan Punyet, 1964-2005 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - N, 1989-2004 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - O, 1985-2007 (Box 4, Folder 16)
      Correspondents include Nathan Oliveira, Claes Oldenburg, and Daniel Ortega.
    - P, 1976-2009 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Q, 1996-2010 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - R, 1969-2010 (Box 4, Folder 19-22)
      Correspondents include Archie Rand, Ad Reinhardt, and Theodore Roethke.
    - Reutersward, Carl-Fredrik, 1984-2006 (Box 4, Folder 23-24)
    - S, 1972-2010 (Box 4, Folder 25)
      Correspondents include Karl Schrag, Peter Selz, Roger Shattuck, Bill Smock, Pierre Soulages
    - S, 1972-2010 (Box 5, Folder 1-5)
    - Shapiro, Ralph Neil [Ashton], 1978, 1991, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Sterne, Hedda, 1976-2002 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - T, 1986-2009 (Box 5, Folder 8-9)
      Correspondents include Mark Tansey, Harold Tovish, William Tucker, and Jack Tworkov
    - Unidentified and Unknown Correspondents, 1965-2010 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - V, 1966-2009 (Box 5, Folder 11-12)
      Correspondents include Regina Vater, Emilio Verdova, Ursula von Rydingsvard.
    - Vassilikos, Vassilis, 1980-2008 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - W, 1977-2007 (Box 5, Folder 14-16)
      Correspondents include Betty Woodman, Christopher Wilmarth, Richard Wilbur, and James Wright.
    - Wadley, Nick, 1989-2010 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - X-Y, 1996-2008 (Box 5, Folder 18)
      Correspondents include Jack Youngerman.
    - Yunkers, Adja, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Yunkers, Alexandra and Marina, 1991-1993, 2009, undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Writings, 1952-1976, undated; 3; 1.6 Linear feet Boxes 5-7
  Miscellaneous typescripts are arranged chronologically, followed by typescripts for specific publications arranged alphabetically by title of publication
  Series 3 contains miscellaneous typescripts for unidentified articles, and typescripts of articles and reviews for various publications including Arts and Architecture and the St. Louis Post-Dispatch.
  - "Avanguadia;" "What Is Avant-Garde?", undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - "Between Cave and Computer", undated (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Guiseppe Capogrossi, undated (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - "Jose De Rivera: A Study", undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - "Donati", undated (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - "Fra Angelico", undated (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Goya, undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Philip Guston, undated (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - "Those Etruscans;" "Sardinia;" "Rome", undated (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - "Paris Letter;" Review of "Nature in Abstraction" Exhibition, undated (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Guston, Stamos, Ippolito; Iaroslav Serpan, Claude Viseux, Mitchell, Lester Johnson, undated (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Hans Hoffman, Kline, De Kooning, Guston, Day Schnabel, Tworkov, Stefanelli, Schapiro; Joan Mitchell, Glarner, De Rivera, Lipton, Guston, Brooks, Hartigan, undated (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - "Interview with George Salles, Director des Musees France", undated (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Gabriel Kohn, undated (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Henri Michaux, undated (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - "Miro's Ceramics", undated (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - "More Than Enlightened: The Olivetti Method", undated (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Motherwell, Mirko, Louis, Bluhm; Dugmore, Morris, Diebenkorn, Stefanelli, Wonner, Mitchell, Goldberg, Nicho Las Marsicano, Stankiewicz, Andrews, Nivola, undated (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - "Report from Rome: Tchelitchew", undated (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - "Jeanne Reynal", undated (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Wols, undated (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - "An Interview with Christian Zervos", undated (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - "St.-John Perse's Guadeloupe", undated (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Italian "Synthesists", undated (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - "Prague Notes", undated (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - French Modernist Artists, undated (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Pre-Columbian Art, undated (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - "Abstract and Non-Objective Art", undated (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - "The Urge to Abstraction", undated (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Position of Abstract Art in Europe, undated (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - "Drawing in Modern American Art", undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - "The Good and the Civilized", undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - "The Age Old Art of Letters", undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Sarasota Catalogue Introduction, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Unidentified Fragments (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Kienbusch, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - "Passage from a Critic's Diary", 1956 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - "Antonio Gaudi", circa 1957 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - "Notes on France and Spain;" Smith, Tomlin, Appel, Woelffer, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - "A View of American Painting", 1958 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Paris Art Scene, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - J.B. Newmann, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - "Americans in Paris;" "The 30th Venice Bienniale;" Avant-Garde Paintings in Prague, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - "Interview with Marcel Jean;" Chamberlain, Leslie, Goodnough, Suzuki, Sawada, Lund, Conner, Natkin; "The Age of Lyricism", 1960 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - "As the Sun Grows Cold", 1961 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - "Lee Bontecou;" Picasso, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Lobdell; Goto; Riopelle; Cohen, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - "James Rosati;" "Portrait of the Artist as Litterateur: Varujan Boghosian", 1964 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - "Assemblage and Beyond;" "Curating Instant Art in History;" "Drawings of Michaelangelo;" "Pastel Anthology", 1966 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Catalogue Introduction for Modern Masters in Miniature "Protest;" "Robert Murray", 1966 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - "Lee Bontecou;" "Deborah Remington", 1967-1968 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - "Use of Manufactured Objects on the Picture Plane;" "Picaresque Episodes of a Great Museum;" "An Open and Shut Case", 1967-1968 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - "Frank Roth", 1967 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - "The Merging Media;" "Merde, Alors!", 1969 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - "Education Through The Arts in Every Sense", 1969-1970 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Abstract Expressionism; Landscape Painting; Elsa Schmid, Stained Glass Artist, 1969-1970 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Preface for Exhibition Catalog, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Review of book Monet by William C. Seitz, undated (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - "Josef Albers;" "Louise Nevelson;" Re: Artist-Sponsored Exhibitions, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - "Miro's Sculptures", 1972 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - "Art and Social Change", circa 1973 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - "A Romantic's Homage to Hans Gerth", circa 1973 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - "Robert Motherwell", circa 1973 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Jack Sonenberg, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Notes for "From Campus to Main Street" Panel at CAA, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Regimenting Cliches Applied to Artists, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - "Jake Berthot", 1973 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - "Paintings by Harvey Quaytman", 1973 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - "Morris Louis, Helen Frankenthaler", 1973 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Philip Guston, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Lee Krasner, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - "Brice Marden's Drawings", 1974 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - "Our Contemporary, de Kooning", 1975 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - "The Poster as Contemporary Genre;" "Introduction: Images of an Era", 1975 (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - "No More Than an Accident", circa 1976 (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - "Philosopher or Dog?", 1976 (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Art and Artist Article, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - Art Bulletin Articles, 1973, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - Art in America Articles, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - Art International Articles, 1962, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 50-51)
  - Arts Articles, 1966-1977 (Box 6, Folder 52-56)
  - Arts and Architecture Articles, 1958-1967 (Box 6, Folder 57-76)
  - Aujourd'hui Article, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 77)
  - Baltimore Museum Bulletin Article, undated (Box 6, Folder 78)
  - Canadian Art Articles, 1963-1964 (Box 6, Folder 79)
  - Cimaise Articles, 1952-1963, undated (Box 6, Folder 80-82)
  - Colloquio Articles, 1971-1976 (Box 6, Folder 83)
  - Contemporary Arts Museum, Houston Article, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 84)
  - Craft Horizons Article, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 85)
  - D'Arts Article, circa 1969-1970 (Box 6, Folder 86)
  - Das Kunstwerk Articles, 1962-1963 (Box 6, Folder 87)
  - France Observateur Article, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 88)
  - Harper's Bazaar Article, undated (Box 6, Folder 89)
  - L'Art Vivant Article, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 90)
  - Le Monde Articles, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 91)
  - London Art News & Review Article, undated (Box 6, Folder 92)
  - London Studio Articles, 1957-1962, undated (Box 6, Folder 93)
  - Motive Article, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 94)
  - New York Times Review of Mortal Victory by Lawrence Hanson, undated (Box 6, Folder 95)
  - Opus International Articles, 1966-1970 (Box 6, Folder 96-97)
  - Plural Article, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 98)
  - Quadrum Articles, 1964, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 99)
  - Review 75 Article, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 100)
  - St. Louis Post-Dispatch Articles, 1963-1965, undated (Box 6, Folder 101-107)
  - San Francisco Evergreen Article, undated (Box 6, Folder 108)
  - Show Article, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 109)
  - Studio International Articles, 1961-1966, undated (Box 6, Folder 110-121)
  - Studio International Articles, 1966-1973 (Box 7, Folder 1-11)
  - XXieme Siecle Articles, 1957-1968, undated (Box 7, Folder 12-14)
- Research files, 1849, 1950-1984, 2009, undated; 4; 3.3 Linear feet Boxes 7-10, ov 15-16
  Arranged alphabetically by the broad topics of books, exhibitions, individuals and miscellaneous topics, then alphabetically by specific name or title
  Research files include materials on Ashton's books, on exhibitions, individuals, and miscellaneous topics. Included are clippings, artworks, photographic material, booklets, brochures, correspondence, and notes. Topics include Angry Art, civil rights, Czech, Polish, and religious art, film, Dadaism, poetry, print-making, and symbolism. Among individuals are Jacopo Luis Borges, Allan Kaprow, Richard Lindner, Seong Moy, Jean Tinguely, Mark Tobey, Jack Tworkov, and Adja Yunkers.
  - Book: Art and Politics in the 20th Century, 1973-1980 (Box 7, Folder 15-16)
  - Book: Art in America Since 1945, undated (Box 7, Folder 17-19)
  - Book: Great Graphic Masters, undated (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Book: In the Shadow of Frenhofer, undated (Box 7, Folder 21-25)
  - Book: A Joseph Cornell Album, 1849, 1943-1977 (Box 7, Folder 26-46)
  - Book: Cutting and Printing Woodcuts, circa 1952 (Box 7, Folder 47)
  - Book: Picasso On Art, 1972-1974 (Box 7, Folder 48)
  - Book: Poets and the Past, 1957-1960, 1984, undated (Box 7, Folder 49-50)
  - Book: A Reading of Modern Art, 1969-1977 (Box 7, Folder 51)
  - Book: A Reading of Modern Art, 1969-1977 (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
  - Book: Recent American Paintings, 1959-1961 (Box 8, Folder 3-5)
  - Book: Response to Crisis in American Art, 1967-1968 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Book: Robert Rauschenberg's Drawings for Dante's Inferno, 1961-1964 (Box 8, Folder 7-8)
  - Book: Rosa Bonheur, 1977-1981 (Box 8, Folder 9-18)
  - Book: Time-Space in the Arts, undated (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Book: The Unknown Shore, 1959-1969 (Box 8, Folder 20-24)
  - Book: Yes, But...A Critical Study of Philip Guston, 1958-1977 (Box 8, Folder 25-44)